We ask a lot of questions
about our diet.
What’s the right way to
treat a chronic illness?
Fight off a virus,
lose weight?
The problem is, we get
a lot of different answers.
Well, I’m here to help.
Welcome to the
Nutrition Facts Podcast.
I’m your host,
Dr. Michael Greger.
Today we continue our series
on Ozempic with the question:
"Why do most users quit Ozempic
and what happens when you stop?”
People may not understand
the potential limitations
of the new class of Ozempic-like
anti-obesity medications,
especially given the wide hype
these drugs are receiving.
For example, the drugs
don’t work for everybody,
and even when they do,
weight loss stalls out
after a year.
The drug insert included
in every package
of the high-dose Ozempic
used for weight loss shows
after about a year,
weight loss stops,
even if you keep injecting
yourself with the drug.
Is it because you’ve plateaued
at a normal weight?
Sadly, no.
They started out obese,
and they ended up obese.
Why does the weight loss
stall out?
Because of what’s presumed
to be a near-exponential rise
in calorie intake,
as the same amount of effort
to cut calories,
whether through willpower,
drugs, or surgery,
is met with
increasing resistance,
as ongoing weight loss activates
your feedback-control circuit,
stimulating your appetite.
So, at first,
the massive GLP-1 activity
triggered by the drugs
lowers your appetite,
but as you lose weight,
your body fights back,
ratcheting your appetite
back up;
so, the same amount
of massive GLP-1 stimulation
causes less
of an appetite suppression.
Within 12 months,
this resistance,
together with the decreased
total energy expenditure
from being lighter,
matches the persistent effort
to cut calories,
and with calories-in
matching calories-out,
weight loss plateaus.
Here it is, graphically.
The same thing happens
whether you’re restricting
calories on a diet,
injecting these fancy new
GLP-1 Ozempic-type drugs,
or going under the knife
for bariatric surgery.
Take high-dose Ozempic.
After the three-month ramp up
in dose,
people are eating nearly
a thousand fewer calories a day.
No wonder they’re losing weight.
But then, the body fights back,
pushing against
the high GLP-1 signaling
and jacking their appetite
back up.
Not all the way back up,
because they’re still injecting
these drugs every week;
so, they still appear to be
eating 400 fewer calories a day
than what they used to.
So, if they’re eating less,
why aren’t they continuing
to lose weight?
Because they’re expending
400 fewer calories
simply because they aren’t
dragging 30 extra pounds
(13 kg) with them
wherever they go.
What happens
if you stop the drug?
In this study, everyone was
started on high-dose Ozempic
for five months
and started to lose weight.
Then, some were randomized
to be unknowingly switched
to placebo injections.
Those who continued
taking the drug,
continued to lose weight,
until the plateau.
Whereas, those who switched
to placebo
started to regain all the weight
they had lost.
It’s the same with tirzepatide,
sold as Zepbound.
As soon as people
stop taking the drug,
the weight starts coming back,
and any benefits
that had been achieved
start to evaporate.
Check it out:
here you can see what happens
when people stop
taking the drug
after being on it
for more than a year.
The pounds pile back on,
two thirds regained
within a year.
Blood pressure came down
with the weight loss,
but then climbed right back up
as if they never even took
the drug in the first place,
and inflammation
and blood sugars
start creeping back up too.
So, not only
does weight loss stop
as soon as you go off the drug,
but the weight you had lost
before comes back.
So, like in this study,
you may have started out obese,
and ended up obese,
and to maintain your
less-but-still-obese status,
you have to keep
taking these drugs,
presumably every day or week
for the rest of your life.
So, these are forever drugs,
the golden goose
for Big Pharma,
drugs for lifestyle diseases
that you may have
to take lifelong,
since you aren’t treating
the underlying cause,
a fattening diet.
As the popularity
of Ozempic-type drugs,
like semaglutide, soars,
what do we need to know
about their effect
on our weight?
Even these newfangled
anti-obesity medications
aren’t a magic bullet.
The overall weight-loss benefits
are notable,
but nonetheless limited.
The best of them can produce
a 20 to 25 percent weight loss,
but they still leave most users
overweight or obese,
only modestly less so,
and, thus, still facing
major health risks.
And, of course,
the drugs are only effective
as long as they’re used.
Not only does
the weight loss plateau,
but years or, presumably,
a lifetime of continuing
treatment is required
just to maintain
their initial benefits,
and most people
stop taking them
within months before even
reaching an effective dose.
The manufacturers
recommend ramping up dosage
over four or five months,
but based on 169,000
real-world patients
using GLP-1 drugs
for weight management,
most individuals didn’t stay
on their prescribed treatment
for even three months,
which suggests
it was unlikely
they were achieving clinically
meaningful weight loss.
In fact, only about half take
the drug for even two months,
and 80 percent quit
by six months.
Why don’t people stick with it?
One reason may be
that these drugs are costly.
And costly is a bit
of an understatement.
The costs of these drugs
are enormous,
like $1,000 a month
in perpetuity,
since any lost pounds
can pile back on
if you stop taking them.
Wegovy, the high-dose Ozempic
used for weight loss,
costs up to about
$1,350 dollars a month.
So, that’s like paying $15,000
out-of-pocket every year.
And some say healthy eating
is expensive?
You could have Food Is Medicine
programs deliver healthy food
to your door for ten times less.
You could even have
fully prepared meals
delivered to your door
at a fraction of the cost
of the drug.
Of course, the drugs
should get cheaper.
There are hopes that competition
will lower prices,
but each GLP-1 drug is protected
by approximately 20 patents,
many up to 2040 or beyond;
so, they probably won’t get
much cheaper anytime soon.
But isn’t obesity itself
expensive?
Even factoring in
health benefits
and discounted prices,
these drugs
may not be cost effective.
In one analysis,
total annual health care costs
doubled for patients,
going from about $13,000
per year
before starting the drug
to $26,000 after.
Now, the benefits of weight loss
accrue over time,
but because lost pounds
are commonly regained
after stopping the drug,
an additional vexing conundrum
is created for payers
like insurance companies.
Why shell out all that money
to get people the drug,
if most are just
gonna stop taking it
and simply regain the weight?
Why are the drugs so expensive?
"There is no rational reason,
other than greed,"
according to Senator Sanders,
noting that Canadians
and Germans
are paying about 10 times less
for the same drugs.
Wegovy, the high-dose Ozempic
used for weight loss,
can sell for $1,300 a month
in the U.S.
but less than a hundred
a month in the U.K.
Here’s what
different countries pay
for the exact same dose
of Ozempic.
The researchers even calculated
the "estimated minimum price,"
how much it could
be manufactured
and sold profitably for.
So, for 40 dollars a month,
Novo Nordisk,
the makers of Ozempic,
could be pulling in
a 10 percent profit margin.
But why make 10 percent profit
when you can make
more than 3,000% profit?
But don’t they need
those huge profit margins
to recoup research
and development?
I mean, it’s expensive
to develop drugs.
Novo Nordisk spends
twice as much money
enriching its shareholders,
by doing things
like stock buybacks
to jack up stock prices,
than it does on all R&D.
In fact,
most big drug companies
spend more on these
kind of self-enrichment schemes
than actual research.
Whatever the actual cost
of developing a drug,
drug companies may spend
far more on marketing drugs
than developing them.
For example, while gouging
patients $1,000 a month
for their drugs,
Novo Nordisk was spending
millions of dollars
wining and dining doctors
to prescribe more of them.
Hundreds of thousands
of meals and snacks
served to promote drugs
like Ozempic.
In fact, Novo Nordisk
was actually suspended
from a pharmaceutical industry
trade association
for failing to disclose
its sponsorship
of a training course
for healthcare professionals
that just so happened
to plug one of its GLP-1 drugs,
a violation bad enough
for the Royal College
of Physicians
to sever its ties
with the drug giant.
Anyway, back to
the original question:
Why do so few people
stay on these drugs?
Well, people may start out
obese and end up obese.
Is it worth paying $1,000
a month just to stay less obese?
You can see why people
might just cut their losses.
But no, the study showed that
most people who quit these drugs
after just a few months
were not only insured,
they had their drugs
covered by their insurance.
So, maybe the reason
most people quit
so soon after starting
is not due to their cost,
but rather their side effects.
We would love it if you could
share with us your stories
about reinventing your health
through evidence-based nutrition.
Go to nutritionfacts.org/testimonials.
We may share it on our social
media to help inspire others.
If you hear about any graphs, charts,
graphics, images, or studies mentioned here,
please go to the Nutrition Facts
Podcast landing page.
There you’ll find all the
detailed information you need –
plus, links to all of the sources
we cite for each of these topics.
My latest major book,
“How Not to Age” is out.
Check it out from your
local public library.
I also wrote a
mini book on Ozempic.
Available in softcover,
e-book, and audio versions.
Check it out on NutritionFacts.org.
And of course, all the proceeds
I receive of the sales
of all my books goes
directly to charity.
NutritionFacts.org is a nonprofit,
science-based public service,
where you can sign up
for free daily updates
on the latest in nutrition research
via bite-sized videos and articles.
Everything on the
website is free.
There are no ads,
no corporate sponsorships,
no kickbacks.
It’s strictly non-commercial.
I’m not selling anything.
I just put it up as a public service,
as a labor of love,
as a tribute to
my grandmother,
whose own life was saved
with evidence-based nutrition.